CLARENCE E. HANCOCK PAPERS (APAP252) 1929-1946
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Clarence E. Hancock Papers 1929-1946
nam_apap252
2.0
Hancock, Clarence Eugene, 1885-1948
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
The Clarence Eugene Hancock Papers document Hancock's time in the House of Representatives in the United States Congress. He was the representative of the 35th District of New York from 1927 to 1945 but came to represent the 36th district from 1945 to 1947 after New York State was redistricted. The collection includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, Congressional bills, transcripts of Congressional hearings, telegrams, and handwritten notes.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Clarence Hancock Papers were originally donated to Syracuse University on September 21, 1962 by Hancock's wife and son. The papers were transferred to M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections at the State University of New York, Albany in 2006.
Biographical Sketch
Clarence Eugene Hancock was born in Syracuse, NY on February 13, 1885 to Theodore E. and Martha Hancock. After public school, Hancock attended Wesleyan University in Middletown Connecticut until his graduation in 1906. Hancock graduated from New York Law School in 1908 and was admitted to the bar in the same year. Once he was admitted to the bar, he began to practice law in Syracuse. From 1916-1917, Hancock served as a sergeant with Troop D of the First New York Cavalry, also known as New York National Guard, on the Mexican border. Hancock next served as a lieutenant with the 104th Machine Gun Battalion in the 27th division during World War One. After the armistice in 1918, Hancock was assigned to work as Assistant Division Judge Advocate and promoted to the rank of captain. Hancock continued to serve in the military until 1919.
After finishing his military service, Hancock returned home and became part of the corporation counsel of Syracuse from 1926-1927 and a trustee of Wesleyan University. During this period, Hancock ran in the Republican primary for mayor of Syracuse but lost the nomination. Then, during the 70th Congress, the current representative of the 35th district, Walter W. Magee, died in office leaving his position open. Voters elected Hancock to fill Magee's position in 1927 and he continued to serve as representative of the 35th district until 1945 when there was re-districting. Hancock was then elected as the representative of the 36th district from 1945-1947. While in Congress, Hancock served on the Judicial Committee, Naval Affairs Committee, and Elections No. 1 Committee. Along with this, he was chairman of the speaker's bureau of the Republican Congressional Committee and head of the Eastern Speaker's Bureau in 1936. Hancock was part of the opposition to President Franklin D. Roosevelt's New Deal plan.
Hancock did not seek reelection in 1946 for the next session of Congress because of a long time illness and the recommendation of his doctor that he should rest. After leaving Congress, Hancock returned to Syracuse to practice law but died in a hospital in Washington D.C. a year later on January 3, 1948. He was survived by his wife, Emily W. Shonk of Plymouth, Pennsylvania, whom he married in 1912, and son, John S. Hancock, born in 1914. He is buried in Woodland Cemetery in Syracuse.
The information provided above was gleaned from the following sources
" C.E. Hancock Dead; Ex-Congressman, 6. " New York Times 4 Jan (1948):52. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/108168688?accountid=14166)
Curran, Thomas J. "Legislative Manuel: New York 1944." Williams Press, Inc: Albany, 1944.
Curran, Thomas J. " The New York red book, 1942: an illustrated publication containing authentic information relating to the executive, legislative, judicial and political affairs of the State " Williams Press, inc: Albany, 1942.
Flynn, Edward J. " Legislative Manuel: New York 1933. " Williams Pres, Inc: Albany. 1933
" Hancock, Clarence Eugene 1885 – 1948. " History, Art, and Archives: United States House of Representatives House.gov. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://history.house.gov/People/Detail/14463?ret=True)
" Interstate Phase of the Insurance Bill. " New York Times 7 Nov. (1943):S10. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/106438954?accountid=14166)
" Moses Leads Against Seabury; Marvin is Gaining. " New York Times 28 Sept. (1934):1. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/101150417?accountid=14166)
" New Yorkers Assigned. " New York Times 13 Dec. (1927):3. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/104033877?accountid=14166)
" Old Guard Leaders Rout Macy Forces, Overthrow Seen. " New York Times 13 Sept. (1934):1. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/101183210?accountid=14166)
" Politics Charged in Deficit Figures. " New York Times 3 Sept. (1936):12. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/101645991?accountid=14166)
" Snell Skeptical of ' No New Taxes '. " New York Times 19 Aug.. (1936):13. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/101811994?accountid=14166)
" Union League Asks War on New Deal. " New York Times 14 Sept. (1934):1. ProQuest Historical Newspapers: The New York Times (1851-2009) with Index (1851-1993). ProQuest. SUNY Albany Library. 24 Feb. 2013 (http://search.proquest.com/docview/100993787?accountid=14166)
Walsh, Michael " Legislative Manuel: New York 1942. " Williams Pres, Inc: Albany, 1942.
" 1942 Election Statistics " Office of the Clerk, House of Representatives. Clerk.house.gov. 25 Feb. 2013 (http://clerk.house.gov/member_info/electioninfo/1942election.pdf)
" 1944 Election Statistics " Office of the Clerk, House of Representatives. Clerk.house.gov. 25 Feb. 2013 (http://clerk.house.gov/member_info/electioninfo/1944election.pdf)
Scope and Content Information
Clarence Hancock was a New York State Representative in the United States Congress from 1927-1947. His collection includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, Congressional bills, transcripts of Congressional hearings, telegrams, and handwritten notes. Much of the correspondence is from constituents and fellow Congressmen, and discusses their opinions about a particular bill and the actions they want taken. The collection covers Hancock's official actions as a New York Congressional Representative from 1933-1946 and does not include personal papers or records of his legislative actions from 1934, 1936, 1938 or 1947. Please note that no papers about Hancock's work outside of Congress or the work he conducted as part of the Naval Affairs or Elections Committees are included in this collection. Some areas of interest in the files include the Equal Rights Amendment, Anti-Trust laws, Submerged Oil Lands, War and Emergency Powers, and Bankruptcy hearings.
The majority of the file names are names that Hancock assigned them based on handwritten slips of paper the archivist found within the original folders in the collection. If there was no paper indicating the file's name, the archivist chose a name based on the subject of the records. All the files are arranged alphabetically. Within the files, items are arranged based on the year of their creation.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics and Politicians; Hancock, Clarence Eugene, 1885-1948; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on the Judiciary.; Bankruptcy--United States; Insurance--United States.; Court rules--United States.; War and emergency powers--United States--History.; New York (State)--Politics and government; Bills (legislative records); Clippings; Correspondence; Notes; Drafts (documents); Transcripts; Legislative records; Congressional Committee Reports
Container List
- Acts, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Administrative Law Bill, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Admission of Evidence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Alien Publication Act, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Anti-Racketeering Act, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Anti-Trust Laws, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bankruptcy – Misc, 1933; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Civil Air Patrol, 1945-1946; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Civilian Defense Compensation, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Committee on the Judiciary, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Committee on Juror Selection, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Court Activities Report, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Court Appropriations, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Court Reorganization, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Court Reporters, 1935-1936; 1939; 1941-1945; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
- Court Reporters, Undated (Flat-file 1)
- Cox Committee, 1943; 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Disqualification of Judges, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Equal Rights Amendment, 1937; 1939; 1942-1945; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
- Government Employee Loans, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Gwynne Bill-HR 2788, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Harrington Bill, 1939; Undated (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
- Hatch Bill, 1939-1940; 1942; 1945; Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Insurance Bill HR3269, 1943-1944; Undated (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
- Insurance Bill HR3269, 1943 (Flat-file 2)
- Insurance Bill HR3270, 1943-1944; Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Insurance Bill (1945), 1944-1945; Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Insurance Bill, 1943-1945; Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Judicial Salaries, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Kefauver Bill, 1945-1946; Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Military Order of the Purple Heart, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Miller-Tydings Bill, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Municipal Bankruptcy Bill, 1937; Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- National Stolen Property Act, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Railroad Reorganization (74th Congress), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Railroad Reorganization, 1945 (Flat-file 3)
- Railroad Reorganization, 1945-1946; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, Record of Hearing (H. Res 145, Report No.203), Vol 1., Undated (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, Record of Hearing (H. Res 145, Report No.203), Vol 2., Undated (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, Record of Hearing (H. Res 145, Report No.203), Vol 3, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
- Second War Powers Act, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Second War Powers Bill, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Submerged Oil Lands, 1939; 1945; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Termination of Temporary Laws, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Tort Claims, 1940; 1942 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- War Contracts Termination, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Wilcox Bill, 1933; Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Wire Tapping, 1942; Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)